# 有荤有素
With meat and vegetables
# 刺激他食欲
It's pretty appetizing
# 海鲜黑椒炒面
Black pepper seafood fried noodles
# 面好了
The noodles are ready
# 你看这面条小魏 提前蒸的
Look at the noodles, Xiao Wei. Steamed in advance
# 就是切面 拌点油
They're just cut noodles. Stir with some oil
# 虾仁腌一下
Marinate the shrimp
# 浆货的东西必须得用纸蘸一蘸
Before marinating, we must use some kitchen towel
# 让它把水汽蘸干了
to remove the moisture of the food
# 你看这多少水
See how much water there is
# 要不然腌的时候就脱糊了
Otherwise the batter will not stick to the food while marinating
# 白胡椒粉 多点少点问题不大
White pepper powder. Doesn't matter if a bit more or less than this amount
# 多点少点问题不大
Doesn't matter
# 盐 海鲜的东西淡一些
Salt. Don't add too much salt to seafood
# 黄酒来一点
Some Huangjiu rice wine
# 香油 它有效的能够去除腥味
Sesame oil. It removes the odor effectively
# 别多了少一点 点到为止
Don't add too much. A few drops would be enough
# 这时候咱们搁蛋清 少来
Now add the egg white. Not too much
# 半个蛋清就足够了
A half of an egg white is enough
# 为什么不搁蛋黄 小魏
Why not use egg yolk, Xiao Wei?
# 清儿起嫩 蛋黄起酥
The egg white makes it tender, while egg yolk makes it crispy
# 这个虾你看这么腌 就腌足了味儿了
See? The shrimp will be full of flavor if marinated in this way
# 先不加粉子 抓起来之后它就黏了
Don't add starch now. The shrimps will become sticky after 'massage'
# 它就整个包裹在上边了
The sauce will cover the entire surface
# 要不然它容易澥
Otherwise the sauce will be diluted and become watery
# 黏糊了咱再起粉子 粉子锁住水分
When it turns sticky, add starch to lock the moisture inside
# 然后再这么着 给它浆上
Then like this... 'Jiang' it (cover the surface with batter)
# 它只能抓 让它把劲抓上
You should only 'grab' it in this way until it becomes tough
# 小魏你看 这很黏
Look, Xiao Wei. It's very sticky now
# 最后封一下油
At last, seal it with oil
# 浆完了开始咱们弄火了
After marinating, let's start cooking
# 胡萝卜 青红椒 香菇 韭黄 洋葱
Carrot, green and red chili pepper, shiitake mushroom, leek sprout, and onion
# 大虾 银芽
Shrimp and 'silver' bean sprout (bean sprout without both ends)
# 豪华版的炒面 点火
That's a luxury version of fried noodles. Light the fire!
# 热锅凉油 再温温它
Hot wok with cool oil. Heat it a bit more
# 你看这时候再弄点凉的
Now add some cool oil again
# 不用动它 行了
No need to stir it too much. It's done
# 咱们先炒料吧
Let's stir-fry the ingredients first
# 洋葱 胡萝卜 香菇
Onion, carrot, shiitake mushroom
# 这些料提前入味
Cook these ingredients first for better flavor penetration
# 再搁（青红椒）银芽
Then the (green and red chili peppers) and 'silver' bean sprouts
# 小魏 行 面条搁里边
Xiao Wei. Now add the noodles!
# 都搁上么 都搁上
-All of these? -Yes, all
# 黑胡椒 就吃这黑胡椒的香味
Black pepper. This dish relies on its aroma
# 这菜名就叫 黑椒海鲜炒面
As the name is 'Black pepper seafood fried noodles'
# 香味出来了 够了吧 蚝油
Here comes the aroma. That's enough. Oyster sauce?
# 够了够了
That's enough
# 白胡椒粉
White pepper powder
# 酱油 够了 这味儿就足够了
Soy sauce. That's enough. Enough flavor
# 少来一点点老抽 一点点
A little bit dark soy sauce. Just a little bit
# 拿筷子 来了
-Get me a pair of chopsticks. -Here you are
# 虾下来
Add the shrimp
# 韭黄
Leek sprout
# 鲜味汁 一点就够
'Savory sauce'. Just a little #理论上这里应该是maggi sauce，不知道为什么每次都用别的字代替
# 这是关键 鲜味汁最后放
That's the key. Add the 'savory sauce' last
# 香啊师父 干香味出来了
That smells great, master. The dry, aromatic smell
# 这炒面 绝了这个
Fried noodles. Awesome
# 这炒面干干净净清清爽爽
This dish is clean and clear
# 黑椒的味儿 这个香
The aroma of black pepper. Smells great
# 小魏这给你 你尝尝我来照
Xiao wei, this is yours. Taste it, let me hold the camera
# 小魏评价评价 不好就是不好
Your commet? Don't worry if you think it's bad
# 海鲜炒面 面的干香
Seafood fried noodles. The dry-aroma of noodles
# 而且您看虾 这种干香气
Also, the dry-aroma of the shrimp
# 完全突出出来了
is emphasized
# 干香
The dry-aroma
# 这黑椒味怎么样 黑椒味很浓
What about the black pepper? The aroma is so strong
# 你看这个菜好在哪
See the trick of this dish?
# 其实咱们下了黑椒
Actually we added black pepper
# 但是黑椒辣度不够
But it's not spicy enough
# 咱用白胡椒粉补充黑椒的辣味
So we use some white pepper powder to compensate for the spicy flavor of the black pepper
# 但是又不夺黑椒的味儿 是吧
But it doesn't compete with the black pepper
# 巧就巧在这儿了
That's the trick
# 师父 不是捧您 确实好
Master, I'm not flattering you, but it's really good
# 我也爱听好话儿
I love such nice words too
# 因为我那阵学徒的时候啊
When I was a apprentice
# 干厨师以后我帮了很多人
I helped a lot of people (with their banquets) after I became a chef
# 当我自己办婚宴的时候
At my own wedding banquet
# 请了我们一个同事
I asked one of my colleagues for help
# 忽然间
However
# 他有一个意外的因素
He was stuck with an accident
# 就是说他不能再帮我办婚宴了
That is, he could not help me with my wedding banquet
# 这个时候我再找别人帮忙
At that time, I asked many other people for help
# 别人都定出去了
But they were all busy
# 我的婚宴就等于没人管了
So my banquet was like, nobody could help with
# 这事让我特别着急
It worried me a lot
# 但是我这人
But I was, myself
# 应该说
I would say
# 我从小经历的
When I was young
# 还是挺多的事儿
I went through a lot
# 我比较也沉稳
So I was somewhat calm
# 我母亲也为我这事挺着急
My mother was also worried about this
# 我说不用着急
I said, 'Don't worry'
# 只要有我在
'As long as I am here'
# 没有过不去
'There's nothing we can't go through'
# 因为我十几岁
Because when I was still a teenager
# 我就可以出走跑外
I could travel to many places on business
# 我跑的地也挺多的
Actually I had been to a lot of places
# 我妈说
And my mother asked me
# 她说婚宴要怎么办
'What are you going to do with your own wedding banquet?'
# 我说我来
I said, I'll do it myself
# 所以我就找了一个
So I asked a colleague
# 我们当时上夜班的一个同事
who was working on his night shift
# 我说你下夜班
I said, 'when you finish your night shift'
# 到我家
'please come to my place'
# 帮我炒个菜
'and help me cook some dishes'
# 有十桌饭
There were ten tables of guests in total
# 所以前期要做很多准备
So we had to do a lot of preparation in advance
# 冷菜热菜这些活谁来管
Who would be in charge of these stuff, like the hot dishes and cold dishes?
# 我说我来办
I decided to do it myself
# 所以我那天说心里话
So on that day, to be honest
# 虽然有幸福感
Though I was filled with the sweetness of marriage
# 但是也有我不快乐地方
I did have some unhappy memories
# 我从头天的早晨上班
I went to work on the morning of the previous day
# 到晚上最晚的一班车
When I took the last train at that night
# 回到南口到家以后
and went back home from Nankou Station
# 九点半了
It was 9:30 pm
# 屋里边有好多朋友都在等着我
A lot of my friends were waiting for me in my home
# 然后把他们明天要帮我干什么活
And I arranged what they should do
# 我都编排好
on the next day
# 然后在我们院子里边
Then in our yard
# 搭了一个大棚
we built a big tent
# 我就自己夜里头
Then I started preparing at night
# 从晚上将近十点半
From about 10:30 pm
# 把所有的菜都放在大棚里头
We put all the food in the tent
# 我从一刀一刀的切
I cut them one by one
# 一个菜一菜的来洗
washed them one by one
# 一个菜来去做
and cooked them one by one
# 整整一直干完了
till the end
# 把凉菜
All the cold dishes
# 6个凉菜
6 cold dishes
# 8个热菜
and 8 hot dishes
# 我都加工了半成品
I processed them into semi-finished products
# 等我再出棚子的时候
When I went out of the tent again
# 你猜几点了
Guess when it was?
# 早上6点
6 am in the morning
# 早晨5:40
5:40 am actually
# 外边这时候挂起了一个七级大风
Then a force-seven wind started outside
# 我一看不行
I thought that, this is not gonna be OK
# 这要在这里边有危险
It would be dangerous to have the banquet here in the tent
# 我就跟我一个旁边的刘大爷
So I asked my neighbor, Liu Da Ye
# 跟他们家商量
I talked to him
# 我说您的房子能不能借我使一天
and asked, 'May I borrow your house for today?'
# 确实
In fact
# 刘大爷和刘大妈毅然决然的
Liu Da Ye and his wife
# 同意了
agreed immediately
# 我特别感激他们
I appreciated their help so much
# 当时我差点眼泪都快出来
I almost burst into tears
# 然后从棚子里边
And moved the dishes from the tent
# 把菜端到他们家
into their house
# 用咱过去那小的煤气灶
I used an old small gas stove
# 一桌一桌的开
To cook the dishes, table by table
# 开了是五回
So in total there were five times
# 一次开两桌
two tables of dish at a time
# 从上午十点开始开桌
The first dish was served from 10 am
# 一直开到晚上六点了
but the last one was served at 6 pm
# 就婚礼前您准备这些
You prepared all these before the banquet?
# 都是我自己准备的
I did it all by myself
# 那大妈知道吗当时
Did Da Ma know about this?
# 她不知道
No, she didn't know
# 因为她在北京么
Because she was in Beijing
# 婚事的在我们这
But the banquet was held in my house
# 您一直也没跟她说
You didn't tell her?
# 自己这些辛苦没说
about what you did?
# 我一看我出来以后
When I looked at myself after finishing
# 我跟土人似的
I was like covered in dirt
# 头天我还特别高兴到饭店
On the previous day, I was so excited when I went to work
# 洗洗澡
I had a bath
# 理理发
and a haircut
# 换换衣服
I also changed my clothes
# 等第二天
But on the second day
# 我干完这一宿饭菜的时候
when I finished preparing all these dishes after a whole night
# 第二天我一照镜子
I looked at myself in a mirror
# 我完全真的又累
I was so tired
# 又疲倦又困
exhausted and sleepy
# 再加上我在看我的形象
And my figure was...
# 人就变了
My figure changed
# 不像个新郎子
I wasn't like a bridegroom
# 洗完了以后
Then I had a shower
# 我就在这到车站
And went to the station
# 去接我的同事
to pick up my colleague
# 她（大妈）8点多一点
She (Da Ma) arrived at my home
# 到我家以后
at about 8 am
# 我把所有的饭菜
After I told my colleague about
# 什么菜都给交代完了以后
all the dishes
# 我说我不管了
I said, 'I can't deal with these any more'
# 我全拜托您了
'They are all yours'
# 他一直干了八桌饭以后
After he finished cooking 8 tables of dish
# 他该走了
He must leave
# 他马上得上夜班
Because he had another night shift
# 晚上还有两桌饭
There were two more tables of dish
# 谁来做
Who could cook those?
# 我就跟我妹又配合
So I was working with my younger sister
# 就在我们家的小厨房
in the small kitchen in my home
# 在我们家小厨房
in my small kitchen
# 我是一边招待客人
I was attending to the guests
# 一边做饭
while cooking
# 做饭我还得悄悄的
But I had to cook 'screctly'
# 我妹我看着水锅
My sister was keeping an eye on the woks
# 看着油锅热了
Like, when the oil temperature was high enough
# 油锅热了我赶快进去炒俩
I went into the kitchen immediately to cook some dishes
# 水锅热了
When the water was boiling
# 赶紧去烫个菜
I hurried to blanch some vegetable
# 然后一炒
Then stir-fry some dishes
# 谁也闹不清楚
So nobody was clear
# 这两桌饭谁做的
Who exactly cooked the last two tables of dish
# 大妈也不知道吗当时
Da Ma was also unaware?
# 这个她知道
She knew about that
# 因为她这时候已经到我们家了
Because she was there in our home already
# 都忙活完了
After everything was finished
# 收拾完了
When we put up everything
# 已经晚上11点了
It was already 11 pm
# 该休息了
Time to sleep
# 人家结婚了
When other people get married
# 该入洞房了
It was time to get into the 'bridal chamber' #请检查这里，感觉怎么翻译都有歧义...
# 我入不了这洞房了
But I could not do that
# 我这两头两条腿往床上一放
When I rested my legs on the bed
# 我都不知道
I didn't even know that
# 这两个腿是我自己的
they were my legs
# 很沉重是吧
Pretty heavy, right?
# 然后我跟大妈也说
Then I told Da Ma
# 我说今天虽然是新婚的夜晚
I said, though this is our wedding night
# 但是我今天确实照顾不了你
I am sorry but I can't take care of you
# 我说我已经累了
I was already tired out
# 两个白天
Two entire days
# 一个夜晚36个小时
and a night, in total 36 hours
# 我没合眼是吧
I didn't even close my eyes for one second
# 所以大妈也流下了激动的眼泪
So Da Ma also cried emotionally